Maddy: In this video we are going to
look at and focus on employees’ rights.
Phillip: Employees are defined as people
who work under an employment contract and
working this way means they have some rights
that other people who work in different
circumstances, don’t have, although, there
are some rights that all workers enjoy.
Maddy: So, let’s have a look at some
of the other rights employees have in
addition to general workers’ rights.
Sickness
Phillip: Statutory sick pay is available If you’re
too sick to work, and your employer has to pay
you at minimum amount a week for up to 28 weeks.
Some employers also have their own sick
pay schemes, for example, workers who
pass their probationary period, might be
eligible for full pay when they’re sick.
Maddy: Statutory maternity leave for
mothers of a new baby, means they
can take up to 52 weeks off work.
This is divided into two blocks of 26 weeks,
called Ordinary and Additional Maternity Leave.
Your employer has to let you return to your
old job at the end of Ordinary Maternity
Leave, or to a similar role that pays the
same and has the same terms and conditions
if you take Additional Maternity leave.
As well as maternity leave an
employee gets Statutory maternity pay.
This means that your employer has to pay you
90% of your average weekly earnings before
tax, for the first 6 weeks, then a minimum
amount 90% of your average weekly earnings
[whichever is lower] for the next 33 weeks.
Phillip: Statutory paternity leave
and pay is also available for fathers.
As a father of a new baby, you’re eligible
to one or two weeks of paid leave and the pay
you’ll receive is a minimum amount or 90% of your
average weekly earnings [whichever is lower].
For those parents who are
adopting there are similar rules.
With Statutory adoption leave, one partner can
take 52 weeks leave, divided in the same was
as maternity leave, while the other partner
can take the two weeks paternity leave, as
already described and Statutory Adoption
Pay works the same way as maternity pay.
Maddy: Shared parental leave and pay is
for when new parents including through
adoption, fostering, or surrogacy and who
want to share their statutory leave and pay.
You can share up to 50 weeks of leave and
37 weeks of pay and the pay is the same as
it is for other forms of statutory leave.
Up to date figures for pay can be found on
the government website so click on the link
below the video for further information.
Phillip: Protection against unfair Dismissal
In certain situations, you may be able
to take legal action if you’re dismissed:
Unfair dismissal is when your employer
dismisses you without good reason, or
if they fail to follow their own formal
disciplinary or dismissal process.
Constructive dismissal is when you’re forced
to leave your job because of how your employer
has treated you, for example if they’ve
refused to pay you or demote you for no reason.
Employees should try and sort out with
the employer any disputes directly or
they can exercise their rights by going
to an employment or industrial tribunal.
Maddy: You have the right
to ask for Flexible working.
This means being able to move your hours,
starting and finishing times, or work
location to be more convenient for you.
For example, working from home, or
starting early so you can finish early.
However, your employer doesn’t have to meet
your requests, but they must deal with them
in a reasonable way, such as by having a
meeting with you to discuss your request.
Phillip: Time off for emergencies.
If an emergency has affected a dependent,
your employer must let you take time off to
care for them, this may include a spouse,
parent, grandparent, child or grandchild.
There’s no limit to how much time you
can take off, but your employer isn’t
obliged to pay you for this time.
Maddy: Statutory Redundancy Pay
If you’re made redundant by your employer,
which means your employer has decided that
they no longer require the job you perform and
that there’s no replacement role available for
you, you’re entitled to receive redundancy pay.
However, you’re only eligible for
this, if you’ve worked for your current
employer for at least two years.
You’ll get half a weeks’ pay for each full
year you were employed under 22, or a full
weeks’ pay for each full year between 22-41.
You receive one and a half weeks pay for
each full year you were 41 and older.
Length of service is capped at 20 years.